After we have learned about the binary search tree, let's see its importance and its time, complexity
and dealing with that.
So consider we have an array, these numbers of array.
And these are the end of this era.
So if we are going to search for a specific number inside this array that contains six elements, I'm
going to search for like four ninety two, so I'm going to go through all the elements all through all
the six elements.
Also, if I'm going to search for like no one, if it is not, it's not included inside the array,
so I'm going to search all the elements in the array.
Also, there is one disadvantage of using array because fixed size, fixed size, when you create the
array in your clothing, you create it with your fixed size like 110, five, one million or whatever
you want.
But if you are going to add the new elements to a fixed size to a fully sized array, you are not able
to do that because we have a fixed size array.
And when it is empty, then when it is full, the array is full.
We can add new elements to it.
OK.
Is just the solution games with the link, at least link at least allow us to add the new elements and
the dynamic addition of new elements without specifying the size of their array or this linkage list.
So for that, we need to to add new notes every time.
OK.
And this will cost us of and because time complex complexity for any insertion or deletion operation,
if we add we are going to add the new node.
We are going to go through all the nodes and we insert it at the end if we are going to delete any of
any node.
We are going to, especially in the worst case that we are going to delete a node that that is at the
end.
So we are going to go through all the elements of this linkage list.
So all of and is the term complexity of any insertion deletion operation.
We didn't find the ideal solution here claims that try to solve all of that previously created problems.
We consider that three, the binary such a tree to the left, we have the minimums and the minimum between
three and then is a three.
And to the left we go.
Minimum one is the minimum element inside the street.
So the most left note inside that binary search three will indicate the menu and the most.
Right would give us the Max.
OK.
In the left, the tree, the lifts up tree, we have six as a maximum because it is the element that
I.
It is the maximum inside the left three and we have maximum inside.
All the whole tree is the most dry element, so the most left element indicates the minimum and the
left and right, and most the right elements will indicate max.
For that, if we are going to search for sex, it's very easy to start by and numbers because we have
A. We divide it to do because we have left or right.
So six is less than eight or greater than eight, it is less than eight.
So we go to the left.
Six is greater than three or less than three.
It is greater than three.
So we go to the right and here we find the solution.
The first step we start by end notes, we go, we are going to search and nodes.
Then when we go to the left, we are going to search for that left some tree.
So that tree we have removed this tree moving will indicate that for us that we are going to search
and over two elements.
And then when we make the next step, when we indicate that six is greater than three, we have removed
the right left sub three.
I will repeat it, guys.
When we go to with the search for all the elements we have and numbers when we go to the left, we have
deleted the right elements.
So we have an over two elements when we reach here.
Six is greater than three.
So we go to the right, so this sub three will be removed.
This for like an ideal solution.
It will indicate for us and over four and this and over four.
And this to that right will indicate for us and over to this left and right will indicate for us and
over two.
So we have eliminated the half of the tree at the first step and we have eliminated that quarter of
the tree at the second step until we find the solution.
So m and over two and over four, let's go and see what is this importance and the time complexity for
finding this solution and searching for specific.
Again, we consider this story if we are going to search for the fort, we go eight city, we go to
the right because four is greater than three.
And we go then to the left because.
Ford is less than six.
This will remain.
And over and over do we have eliminated the half of elements?
We have eliminated a quarter of the elements and we have intimidated that and over eight elements to
find the four.
No.
In order to search for any number, we follow the path that it is.
Start by M. We eliminate going to the left or right.
So and over two.
Then we go to the left or right.
So it will indicate and over four, it will eliminate and over four of the elements then and over eight
and over 16 and so on, until reaching the desired and the correct note that we are going to search
for.
OK.
No.
And and then over to I will put them inside this shape like a fraction.
Now this fraction indicates for me that one, two, four and eight, it's multiple of two.
So it will transform it to and to power one and power zero and the power to and to power city and so
on.
These elements will give us an equation and over 2K Gay is zero, one, two, three and four and so
OK.
And over City or and over two and over 2K will give me one because I will find the solution later on.
So the solution of this mathematical equation and equal to K I multiplied 2K by one and an equal two
to power k no.
Let's log both sides to base two logging look due to power to power K equal to log to end.
OK, log to the base to find.
Look to power Kate at the base to way to give us two.
Sorry, Kate, because two and two will go and eliminate each other when logging in the same base.
And we have power of the same base where they eliminate each other like equal log and two bass.
Two.
OK.
No.
Came to power a lot.
This is the equal look to the power.
Our look and the base to OK.
Please save this.
When we have an array here, we are going, we have eight elements going through six elements to find
the result.
So if I'm going to search for any number, we are going to search through all the elements to find the
result.
So consider you are searching for number one.
You will go through all the elements and you will not find no one.
So you go through eight elements.
This going through elements and searching through all the elements will give us the complexity of of
that.
Now, in binary, such a theory going through if we are going to search for six, so we are going through
three elements to find the result.
We start by one.
We are six is less than eight.
Yes, so go to the left six greater than three.
Yes.
So go to the right.
And then we find six going three through all the elements will give us like an array while in the binary
such a tree.
Going through three elements to find the result will give us a more and faster way to find the elements.
So we have in total in any binary search tree, get the elements, how many number of elements we have
in this tree we have eight.
So OK, equal to log to log eight to base two, log two, a log eight base two will give us three.
So we have gay equal to three iteration to find the result.
Therefore, the the binary search tree has a complexity of log and log and is faster than an ancestor
than square ancestors than any think other than before.
OK.
This is.
The importance and this is the time complexity of binary search a tree.
It is luck.
And in the worst case scenario.
Let's see at table the binary statutory complexities when we deal with the best case scenario and the
average case scenario and worst case scenario or complexity in searching the binary, the binary tree
in searching will give us luck.
And in the best case, the worst case will give us all of and in the worst, worst case game in searching
look log and one of the worst cases of and deletion will give us look and hear.
The worst case will give us off.
But the average case complexity is more applicable in binary search tree because you have logjam and
this is more logical than the worst case complexity.
OK.
Worst case complexity, like having a tree that contains only one note, so you are going to go through
this node.
So we have and not log.
OK.
Here is the number of notes into three legs, a space complexity, the space complexity for all the
operation is of and this is about the binding of such three and how it is very important to make.
The time complexity of it and how to use it.
And why it is important, and we have seen many example about that, so when dealing with numbers or
any order thing, please use the binary search tree because it is the fastest way, the fastest data
structure to be or there to be to be dealing with and so on.
So this is all about the binary search.
Three will see beasties in their exercises, in their exams that we are going to solve in the exercises
section.